All right. Good morning. How's everybody doing? Awesome. Man, you guys sound good, and I assume you look good. I can't see anybody from this perspective. I got lights right here, so we're going to be blind, and good luck. It'll be great. Hey, if you're joining us online, we're excited that you are joining us this morning from the Alamo. I'm excited to be here today.
I'm excited about this because I didn't have to preach to a camera this week. I don't know if you guys have had the misfortune of having to watch one of the online services. You guys have stuck around for so much of that. Thank you so much. I just am not good at talking to a camera. Maybe it's because as we dive into today's message, we'll find out that I have a little pride and arrogance happening inside of me, and I just need the feedback. I need to know that I'm loved and adored and appreciated and all that good stuff.
Man, I already feel better. Don't y'all feel good? To be able to allow you guys to join in and see us from here is actually a huge blessing. Maybe us losing the studio was good for everybody, even those online, because then we had to figure out how to make this happen from here, and here we are. We'll see how it goes, and it'll be good. Before we jump into today's message, first of all, I would love
to take credit for this and say, "You know what? We're just that darn smart and well planned out," but that's just not true. Today is World Mental Health Day, which is interesting because I'm going to talk a lot about mental health today. How did that happen? Well, God is in charge. We really did not plan this out this way because I'm not smart enough to know when that special day is or any special day is.
And so here we are. So as we navigate into today's message, I want to say this. My prayer today is that we would let today's message speak to us personally. And what I mean by that is this, is we're going to spend some time today contrasting a couple things, all right? And as we spend time contrasting these specific things, we're going to be talking
about the worldly kingdom versus the secular kingdom. We're going to be talking about a worldly king versus a godly king. We're going to be talking about a man who is living life by the Spirit versus a man controlled by an evil spirit. And as we talk about those things, my hope and my prayer today is this. My fear is, and one of the things that I worry that we in the church do so often that I think
can actually be dangerous and is the reason why so many people land in a spot where they get hurt by individuals in the church is this. I think we often put ourselves in the mind. We are always the hero in the story. And so my prayer today is this, is that we would have a humble posture. In fact, a lot of what we're going to be talking about today and diving into is the issue of pride. And so I'm going to humbly ask, and we're
going to pray before we get started that you would approach today by saying, God, would you reveal to me some areas in my life where I reflect a secular kingdom versus a godly kingdom? God, would you in my life point out areas where I try to set up my own kingdom versus work and participate in your kingdom?
But I think if we're not careful, we roll into this automatically assuming we have just been doing it right because, gosh darn it, we're just so good at all that we do.
And I think a lot of where we are in our culture and a lot of where we are as far as a church, and when I say church, I mean like the big C church, all churches, I think a lot of where we are is because we often call to take the humble servant approach in so many things.
And you'll do that in a big way today. So, would you pray that God would speak to you, point out inconsistencies in your life that are not consistent with his kingdom?
And then, as we're going to see Nebuchadnezzar do today, do the very thing that Jesus provided you the opportunity to do, and it's this: Repent. Change direction. Do something different.
Because the reason we gather here or watch online on a regular basis is because a good bit of us in this room, a good bit of us watching, have made the decision that Jesus is the God and the Lord of our life, and we believe following him and doing what he says to do is a better way to live.
If that's the case, he's given us the opportunity by what he did on the cross to simply change directions and go a new direction. That direction is towards him and towards his kingdom.
So, let's pray that God will do that, and let's jump into today's message. Father, we love you.
And God, we truly believe that your kingdom, that following you, doing what it is you've told us to do, is a better way.
But God, sometimes, if we're not careful, we get so easily distracted.
And God, we allow that distraction to cause us to do things that we never thought we would do.
Allow that distraction, God, to creep into our life and produce pride and arrogance.
And God, every time that those things are present in our lives, it is contrary to what your kingdom is.
It's contrary to how you would call us to live our lives.
It's contrary to how you lived your life while walking on earth to show us a better way to live.
So, Father, today, would you, through your Holy Spirit, not through me or God, help me to not come across as prideful or arrogant today.
Father, help me to clearly articulate humbly your word this morning.
And God, would your Holy Spirit work in our lives where there are things that are present that are contrary to your kingdom, which we believe is a better way to live.
God, would you point that out and then give us the wisdom.
And the courage to confess to you where we have failed.
And then God began to walk the direction you called us to walk because, again, we believe it is a better way to live.
We love you. We praise you. We thank you that you love us.
It's in Jesus' name we pray. And all of God's people in the house said, "Amen."
And I'm sure you said it online. I just couldn't hear you. So, awesome.
Or maybe if you were a little louder, just yell really loud into your computer or TV screen. Amen.
So we can hear you here.
That was corny. All right. We can't do it. All right.
Hey, if you got your Bibles, do me a favor and go to Daniel chapter 4. Daniel chapter 4.
This is a really, really fun story that happens in Daniel chapter 4.
I preached this a long, long time ago. Like, I think Canvas was maybe a year old or something like that.
And we did a series we called The Crazy Ones, and we ended up on this passage.
And I have no idea how prophetic that this passage might have been in me becoming the director of the mission and so on and so forth.
And so really a fun and special passage that we get to dive in today.
And if you're not familiar with this passage, by the time we leave today, you're going to be glad that you are, I hope.
And I would also say this. There are a lot of verses in this passage.
I'm not going to read all of those verses to you today in that passage because I don't want my education to go.
And so, that was a joke. It's just a fun story. I'm going to chase a rabbit for three seconds and we're going to get back on.
I was in a seminary class one time, and the professor started reading to us from the book.
And it just frustrated me so much because I thought, "I am a grown man."
And this is probably my arrogance. I won't talk about that in a minute.
I can read myself. I didn't come here for you to read to me. I've got things I need to do.
So, I kind of made a decision that day. I don't want to be the kind of communicator that gets up and reads to you,
unless it's absolutely necessary. So, all that to say this.
You want to go back and you want to read this whole thing in its entirety because it's so good.
But I trust that you are big people and you own a Bible. And if you don't, let us know. We'll give you one.
You can read the full story in its entirety and get all the details because it's all good.
Plus, I knew that if I read through, I would want to stop and comment on every bit of it.
And we'd be here until four o'clock this afternoon. I got things to do. So, there we go. All right.
And you do too, I'm sure, but I'm on me because that pride thing we're going to talk about here in a minute.
All right. And I am off here.
All right. So here, let me let me paint a picture happening here and how we've got to where we are in Daniel chapter four.
So if you remember in chapter one, Pastor Ryan did an incredible job speaking through chapter one and he did what I should do.
I took two weeks to get through the passage rather than me trying to get it all Sunday because he's more godly than I am.
And so but he did a great job helping us see how a group of young men are brought into captivity, stripped of their identity,
stripped of the opportunity to be with their family, stripped of the opportunity to be known as they had always been known
and forced into following a secular way of living or a way that is against the way God would have them to live.
They are brought into and indoctrinated and forced to serve in that environment.
OK, and so he spent a great two weeks unpacking that for us and explaining that.
Then we briefly went through chapter 2. Chapter 2, again, Nebuchadnezzar has a dream.
Daniel is called in to interpret that dream, and basically what Nebuchadnezzar gets out of that dream is,
"I'm awesome, and I should build a gold statue that all can see because I am the gold head."
And so, yee-haw, look at me, right? So he does that, and then chapter 3 happens.
We talked about this last week. Shadrach, Meshach, and a while ago get together, and they decide,
because this has been together, anyways, they made a decision early on at a young age,
we are going to live our life in honor of the God of the Bible, the God of our ancestors, right?
And so that was their decision that they made long before the opportunity came for them to make the stand.
We talked a little bit about this last week, that oftentimes in the American Christian church,
what I'm afraid we do is we see something we don't like and then make the decision to take the godly path,
rather than having already made that decision, living that decision out,
and when there is friction against how we live, we're not jerks about it,
but we just remain faithful to what we've always done.
Sometimes I fear that in the Christian church in America, we just chase drama rather than Jesus,
and that gets us into big trouble. So, last week was about us remaining faithful to the thing that God has called us to do,
and then we believe that our God will be faithful to us. And the way we saw the story play out is,
they were thrown in the fire, and Jesus shows up. And we talked about this last week,
that any time that we are faithful to Jesus, we get thrown into the fire, the beauty of our faith is this,
is that our God walks with us. He doesn't often remove the fire. He walks with us in the fire.
And that, often times, is way better than him removing the fire, because it leaves an incredible testimony to who he is and who he does.
All right? And that leads us to today, chapter four. So if we're going in order, you had chapter one, two, three,
and now we're in four. Man, look at that. That Arkansas education is paying off. All right?
So in chapter four, here's what happens in chapter four. This is where things start to get really good.
By this time, Daniel is becoming a more mature man. He is probably 45 to 50 in this time.
And has, again, been faithfully living out a commitment that he made as a young man.
And so by this time, he has been working in or been in Babylon for somewhere in the range of about 30 years.
I think what happens sometimes, because here, in a couple weeks, we're going to get to Daniel in the lion's den.
And I think what happens, because we learned it in Sunday school, sometimes we think that Daniel was like a kid when the lion's den thing happened, right?
Well, he was a mature man, all right? Maybe mature might be, because I know some guys who are 45, and I don't know about maturity sometimes.
But, nevertheless, that's how this plays out. So, this passage is so fun, because a lot of things happen in this passage.
Like, Nebuchadnezzar is going to go crazy in this passage. He goes crazy, and he disappears for seven years.
And in that time, when he disappears for seven years, he's like living out in the yard, in grass. It is just insanity.
And then he comes back at the end of that seven years, and he becomes king again.
Could you imagine a world where the president goes crazy for seven years, and then is just reinstated back to president like nothing ever happened?
Like, well, okay.
All right. I really set up for that one, didn't I? In a lot of ways, a lot of ways.
We've lived a lot of life in the past several years in our country.
It's just been fun. Anyway, so here's what happens, all right?
He disappears, he comes back, and he gives an address based on what happened.
All right? And that's where we pick up in verse one.
King Nebuchadnezzar sent his message to the people of every race and nation and language throughout the world.
Now, when he's sending it throughout the world, he is in charge of a good bit of the world at this point.
So that's why he sent it out, because that's where he's at.
So here's what he says, "Peace and prosperity to you.
I want you all to know about the miraculous signs and wonders the Most High God has performed for me.
How great are his signs, how powerful his wonders, his kingdom will last forever, his rule through all generations."
It seems as if Nebuchadnezzar has truly had a heart change.
Now, we can argue whether or not that's the case, but it seems as we read through this.
Verse 4, "I, Nebuchadnezzar, was living in my palace in comfort and prosperity."
So he's letting everybody know in his decree. Here's what I want you to know.
I was doing a really good job, and I had everything that I wanted.
Like, I am really proud of me, and all the things that I had accomplished at that point.
And so, I was living in a place of prosperity. I was living in a place that nobody could touch me.
I was living in a place where I was secure from everybody. Nobody could get to me.
Here's one of the fears that I have in our current culture. Here's one of the fears that I have for my generation,
and maybe generations that are younger than me. So, I'm getting to a place where I'm becoming the old man who's getting cranky.
And I know some of you don't think I'm that old, because I know there are some in this room that are a little bit more mature than me in age.
However, I feel like in my young age, if I can call myself young, I'm right at that, like, weird spot,
where some of you in the room think I'm old, and some of you in the room think I'm still a child. So, that's where I live right now.
But, I'm getting to that place where I feel like I'm just, I've lived so much that I'm getting just cranky,
and looking at the younger generation going, "They're going to mess it all up."
And I realized, generation before me thought we were going to mess it up. Anyways, part of the deal, right?
But I think one of the fears that I see happening in our culture is we are just, we are so in love with the idea,
and maybe even it's become our God in some aspects of being safe and secure.
It's a fear that I have, that we want safety and security so much more than we want faithfulness to God.
Because I'll say this, I'm not certain following Jesus is safe and secure.
We can talk a lot about that throughout Scripture. Now, I will say this, because I think you have to, you know, you have to put parentheses around that.
That doesn't mean we act foolish or neglect opportunities for safety and security just because.
All right? Does that make sense? I don't think it's wise to live in one extreme or that or the other.
I just think we can't allow safety and security to be the thing that keeps us from being faithful to the God that we've been called to serve.
Okay? So, I think the point that he's making here is I was safe, I was secure, and nobody could touch me. Nobody could get to me.
I had what I wanted, could do what I want, and nobody, because I was, at this point, the most powerful king, nobody could get to me that I didn't want to get to me except God.
God can get to anybody he wants to, at any time he wants to do it.
This is important for us to remember, because so many times in our culture, among ourselves, we will come against, we will have a moment where we're dealing with somebody who is absolutely impossible to deal with, and when we're dealing with that person who is absolutely impossible to deal with, we will make statements
like nobody is ever going to get to them. And that's just not true, because we serve a God who can get to anybody at any moment of his choosing. I struggle with the doom and gloom that sometimes we as followers of Jesus have, when we don't like policies and decisions and leadership
that is above us, that we just act like the world is coming to an end when the truth is we serve a king who is above that king, and at any moment if that king who is above that lower king decides to make a decision for change, he can, and nothing will stop him.
It's so important for us to understand that in the midst of King Nebuchadnezzar being powerful, having everything that he could have ever desired, including all of the safety, all of the security an individual could want, God can breach all of that.
And he does, as we continue to see how this plays out. So he then goes in, and he tells the story of the dream that he had. But before he gets that, he starts to talk about the dream.
And he did what Nebuchadnezzar, we've seen do in the past, because we watched him do this in chapter 2. He calls for somebody to help him interpret the dream.
So he calls, and he requests for Daniel to come. So verse 9 tells us this, "I said to him about the Shazzar, chief of the magicians."
Now, that's, so do you remember that story last week? Because I know all of you paid so close attention to everything that I say.
So you guys remember that clearly. But that wasn't their given names, right? Their names, I forgot what they were, but they were godly names.
Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego are not their godly names. They were, they were the secular names, right?
So Daniel's given name when he came to Babylon was Belteshazzar. Belteshazzar means Baal will protect.
Could you imagine being stripped away from your family, being stripped away from your homeland, being stripped away from your culture, and then given a name that is completely offensive to everything
you've ever grown up being taught? That's Daniel's situation here. So even in the midst of this, I want you to check this out. This is really important.
I said to him, Belteshazzar or Daniel, chief of the magicians, I know that the spirit of the holy gods is in you and that no history is too great for you to solve.
Here's something that we see about Daniel that Nebuchadnezzar saw in Daniel, even though he had all of the theology
surrounding it completely wrong. Nebuchadnezzar had all the theology wrong, was even pointing to the wrong God.
However, here's the reality. He knew there was something different and powerful about Daniel. What was different and powerful
about Daniel is this: he had the Holy Spirit living in him. And when you have the Holy Spirit living in you, that is more
powerful than anything else. We live, I think, in a time, in a day and an age. Now, I need you to listen to
me very carefully, because if you don't listen to me carefully here, I promise I will get an email about
this. So hang tight before you get sidetracked, okay? You with me? I need some commitment in the room
on this. Okay, thank you, because if we don't have commitment, I'm gonna get an email, and then I'm gonna be
not happy, okay? Because I'm gonna be like, I told you, I warned you to hang with me before I finish, right?
We live in a culture right now that elevates education and things like that above Holy Spirit.
Now, don't misunderstand me, okay? This is the point where everybody gets sideways. I believe, down to my socks, that education is
extremely important, okay? But if education is disconnected from Holy Spirit, I think we can get in trouble.
We can get in trouble really quick. So you have to understand that Daniel is surrounded by educated individuals
who, through their education, have learned to tap into incredible things, like being able to do magic, okay?
Now, I don't want to get into some of the other things that could be into this because I just don't have time, but here's the point.
He's surrounded by highly educated, wise individuals in their fields, but something was special about him,
and the thing that was special about him is the Holy Spirit. Holy Spirit power, every single time,
is greater than any other thing we can achieve or purchase. You with me?
So, when Nebuchadnezzar needs somebody to lay out some stuff, who does he call on? He calls on the one with the Holy Spirit.
And says, "I need you to interpret this. I need you to do what only you can do."
Here's what I want to remind you of. We have, as followers of Jesus, an incredible responsibility to consistently be tapped into the Holy Spirit.
The thing that I think is most powerful about Daniel is his consistency in his walk with Jesus that allowed the Holy Spirit to consistently
lead him, which gave him wisdom, and it gave him favor in lots of situations where you and I would not have been invited into the room
because our consistency is not as equal to what Daniel was doing. Does that make sense? Something powerful about this.
It's why he wanted him to be in the room. When everything goes down, Neb wants him in the room because of his connection
to the Holy Spirit, even though he couldn't figure out that's what it was. Interesting, right? So he comes in, and Nebuchadnezzar
Nebuchadnezzar tells him the dream, and so the dream in a gist is this. You can go back and read it later
because I'm probably going to butcher most of it. So again, don't get mad. Just go read it yourself.
He has a dream of a big tree in the middle of the earth, and this tree is a really important, powerful tree,
and people eat from the tree. You know, everything is fed and nurtured from this tree, and then a messenger from God
comes down and chops the tree down, but leaves the stump, and the stump is connected to a bronze,
is bound to the ground with a band of iron and bronze, all right? So he chops everything down, leaves the stump,
and the stump is in the roots of the ground bound with a band of iron and bronze, all right?
So Nebuchadnezzar tells Daniel the dream, and Daniel does what only Daniel can do because of the presence
of the Holy Spirit in his life. Daniel tells him what the dream means. This is where things get really good.
So when Nebuchadnezzar hears from God, and he didn't understand, he calls Daniel, and Daniel explains the dream
to him, and it goes something like this in verse 19. "Upon hearing this," ooh, this is so good, also known as Belteshazzar, right?
So upon hearing this, Daniel, this is so important, "was overcome for a time, frightened by the meaning of the dream.
Then the king said to him, Belteshazzar, don't be alarmed by the dream and what it means."
Belteshazzar replied, "I wish the events foreshadowed in this dream would happen to your enemies, my Lord, and not you."
You've got to get an understanding of the picture that's happening here. Nebuchadnezzar, in all ways, is the enemy of Daniel.
It is his leadership, it is what he has done that has caused Daniel to end up in slavery, to be disconnected from his family.
He's told your culture, "Everything that you are is wrong. Follow our rules, follow our customs, follow what we do."
Nebuchadnezzar is responsible for that.
And 30 years into this, it's not like a bad day, or a bad week, or a bad couple years. It is a bad 30 years.
Nebuchadnezzar tells him this dream, and Daniel's response was, "Dang skippy, buddy, it's finally coming.
You're going to get what's been coming to you for a long time. This is good news."
That was not his posture. That would have been our posture, potentially, right?
Our posture was like, I knew at some point God was going to get you. Hot dog.
Finally, what I've been praying for is going to happen, you know? I don't know what happened there. It's good.
But that's not his posture. His posture is this. I wish I wasn't having to tell you this.
I wish I'm about to tell you what happened to your enemies and not you, king.
What's so powerful here is this. Daniel, because of the power of the Holy Spirit in him, loves his enemy in such a way that the failure and the destruction of his enemy makes him sad.
Far too many of us in this room who claim to be followers of Jesus, that claim that the Holy Spirit lives in us, get way too excited when we have the opportunity to deliver correction to our enemies.
The Spirit of God living in us gives us a different perspective when it comes to delivering news to our enemies. Daniel, being sensitive to the Holy Spirit, has grown to love the very person responsible for all of the evils in his life.
So much so that when he gets a word that God is going to bring destruction, it bothers him. And here's essentially what Daniel tells him. What this dream means, verse 24, your majesty, and what the most high has declared. Now this is an interesting word, what the most high has declared.
This is all the time, but let me let you in on a secret here. Again, I don't think he's being disrespectful in his, in his demeanors. Maybe I will come across as I'm saying this, but he says, "Someone who is higher than you, you think you are in charge. You think you are awesome, but let me let you in on a secret here, King. Someone higher
than you has declared that this is going to happen." I want to just take a quick detour here and say this. We, as followers of Jesus, have always got to remember, God is in control.
However you thought, let me say this carefully, however you thought our current president became the current president, I know there's a whole lot of, let me let you in on a secret.
However it is, whatever it looks like, whatever you think that he became president, let me let me tell you how it really happened.
God let it happen. That's all throughout Scripture. You don't have to like it. You don't have to agree with it. That's just true.
God is in charge of all of that. That should both give us a peace, while at the same time scare us a little bit to think, "Hmm, if God can do that there,
what could he do in my life if I'm not careful, if I'm not where I need to be?" And that's a whole other--we'll get to that in a minute.
Here's my point. King, no matter how powerful you are, no matter how awesome you think you are,
there is somebody greater than you. And just as he allowed you to come to power, he can take you away that fast.
And that's what's going to happen. So Nebuchadnezzar goes on and he says, "Most highs, declared, will happen to my Lord the king.
You will be driven from human society, and you will live in the fields with the wild animals. You will eat grass like a cow,
and you will be drenched with the dew of heaven. Seven periods of time will pass while you live this way
until you learn that the Most High rules over the kingdoms of the world and gives them to anyone he chooses.
But the stump and the roots of the tree were left in the ground. This means that you will receive your kingdom back again
when you have learned that heaven rules. Dude, this is an intense word right here.
In other words, when you repent, when you change the way you're doing things, God will give it back to you.
That's so crazy. And then here's what he says.
King Nebuchadnezzar, listen to the way he says this. Accept my advice. Stop sinning and do what is right.
Break from your wicked past and be merciful to the poor. Perhaps then you will continue to prosper.
You see, if Daniel had not had Holy Spirit power, if Daniel had not learned to love his enemy,
Daniel might have left that part out. Hey, bro, you keep doing what you're doing. Man, you do it, bro.
Hot dog. And secretly begin to develop an opportunity for a coup. Hey, guys, come here. We've got to talk for a second.
Man, this is going to sound crazy, but trust me on this. If Neb keeps doing what he's doing, I've got some inside information here.
Here's what's going to happen. He's going to go crazy, and when he goes crazy, we can take over.
Now, I guarantee here's how they did that. They would have said it, you know, somewhere along this line.
You know, I wouldn't really want to take over, but you know, I mean, you know, if me being in charge means God gets to be in charge,
well then, you know, praise God, that's the way we need to do it.
Daniel could have done some serious positioning here, but he doesn't. He remains faithful to God and to the king who God chose to be in charge.
So he says, "King, please, please hear what I'm saying. Repent. Change your ways."
And then maybe God won't let this happen. Maybe it'll end differently for you.
Here's what I want you to know. If you're here today, repentance changes everything.
Look at the difference between these two. You have Nebuchadnezzar who is free, Daniel who is a slave.
You have Nebuchadnezzar who is filthy rich, Daniel who is poor.
You have Nebuchadnezzar who has a harem, and you have Daniel who is single.
These two individuals could not be any different. Yet, there was one who had perceived power, and then there was one who actually had power.
And the difference is Nebuchadnezzar had perceived power because he thought he was that good.
He thought he had done some good things. And then you have Daniel who had Holy Spirit power, which changed everything.
That's where the power was. So, Daniel's advice to Nebuchadnezzar was this. And it's what we say all the time.
We talk about we believe Jesus came to die and reconnect us to the Father, but we also believe Jesus came to show us a better way to live.
I would say this added to it. I don't think our goal as followers of Jesus is to just simply do what Jesus wants us to do.
I believe another, maybe even more important component to that is this. We not only want to do the things that Jesus wants us to do,
but beyond that, we should always do the thing that Jesus died that gave us the ability to do, and that's this: repent.
Jesus never had to repent. You and I? That should be a regular practice.
Why? Because we are so much more messed up than we think we are.
And if you're listening to me this morning and you don't think you're that messed up,
if I could tap into Daniel here for just a moment, with all the love in my heart, can I tell you,
you probably need more repentance than anybody else in this room, or watching online.
Our need for Jesus is even greater than we think it is, and if we don't think it's that great, then we need it that much more.
Daniel understood that. Daniel presented that. And I want us to see this, too.
I gotta go so fast, guys. Just listen, like, as quickly as you possibly can. Just, like, pretend that you have, like, supercharged ears on, okay?
Here's what happens when Daniel talks to King Nebuchadnezzar.
He shares this story that, first of all, King, you need to repent.
And then he shows us this, and we see this all throughout Scripture. God often warns, and then he waits, because he's a patient God.
He has to give everybody the opportunity to change, to repent, to go a different direction.
So Daniel tells him that. But I think the secret sauce to the way Daniel shares this message with Nebuchadnezzar is this,
is clearly Daniel forgave before he delivered this word.
I heard a pastor teaching on this, and he said this, "Before you correct, you need to connect."
Daniel has an extreme amount to forgive Nebuchadnezzar for.
Because of Nebuchadnezzar, Daniel has to be a vegan. Because of Nebuchadnezzar, Daniel is in slavery.
And there's a lot of debate on this. Who knows?
But because of Nebuchadnezzar, there's potential that Daniel was castrated.
Got to be real with y'all. That's going to take a lot of forgiving.
Daniel clearly had before, "When you give a hard word, do it with a tender heart."
I think too many times, Christians, when we get the opportunity to give a hard word, we get excited.
And that is completely the opposite of the way our king operates and calls us to operate.
I believe delivering a hard word with a prideful heart
I believe that's called being a Pharisee, and Pharisees are probably the greatest tool of the devil.
That's why so many people walk away from the church.
Because we have a message from God, and we use, we yield that word, that truth, with a prideful, arrogant heart.
And that destroys people. Our team came to give life, life to the full.
We have a responsibility to yield the truth we've been given with the utmost wisdom and utmost tender heart we could possibly have.
I believe this: it's easier for people to hear you if you love them.
Our culture seems to have lots and lots of experts who know the way, and very few friends who share things in love.
I think the reason this works so well was Daniel truly showed a love for Nebuchadnezzar that he had probably never heard from anybody.
I would also say this: in an instant gratification world, don't give instant words of correction.
If God lays it on your heart, because there's always those people, "God, I was praying the other day, and I saw something that you posted on Facebook, and God just let me tell you you shouldn't do that."
Stop. Stop that crap. It doesn't help anybody.
If you've not shed tears for that person before you uttered that word, just be quiet.
I am so tired of well-meaning Christians sharing well-meaning thoughts that did not come from a place of love, but it came from a place of pride and arrogance.
I am above you because God laid this on my heart, and I'm going to tell you because I am so godly, and you, well, you're just not.
Daniel's heart was broken for the very enemy that ruined his life, so much so that he delivers this from a place of a broken heart.
If you cannot deliver correction from a broken heart, don't do it. Write that down. I will not correct anybody until my heart is broken.
Because to be frank, you're doing way too much damage to the church when you do that crap.
Because our God is not a God who delivers rebuke without a broken heart first.
Sorry, I didn't mean to go there, but there we went.
So we move on. I'm gonna have to go real fast. I'm almost done.
Not really. All right, just play those fingers out, man. It's good.
So here's what happens. All these things did happen to Nebuchadnezzar.
Twelve months later, what Nebuchadnezzar does, he goes up at the roof of his palace, and he's looking over everything that he's built.
He's looking at the hanging gardens that he built, one of the seven wonders of the world.
I'm not going to read it because I don't have time, but here's what happens. He's looking over that, and he, with arrogance and pride, goes,
"God didn't do what he said he was going to do. Look at all that I am. Look at how powerful I am. Look at how good I am."
And he's in a place where I think he's looking down, and he's looking down on the people that he was supposed to be serving,
he looked down on them, over them, and I bet his thoughts were something like this,
"At least I'm not like them, and maybe that's why God spared me." And just as he was talking, it's like mid-sentence.
God said, "No, no, no, bro. I'm in charge." And instantly, he fell crazy. And he did exactly what God said would happen.
He went and spent seven years living in the yard eating grass.
Could you imagine CNN or Fox reporting on that daily? King Neb's still, you know, crazy.
And then down the road, what happens is he finally looked to God.
And when he did, he instantly was healed.
Nebuchadnezzar takes his eyes off the God who created him, and because of that, becomes this one that was created.
He becomes an animal.
Anytime God is not our primary focus, we have the tendency to fall into animalistic behaviors.
The world is usually described as what? Dog-eat-dog-world.
Why? Because that's how a Babylonian kingdom works.
Our kingdom is far different than that. Now again, for seven years, Daniel has the opportunity to take over, but he doesn't.
He stays faithful to the king, and the king comes back. I do want to touch on this for just a second.
I'm over, so I have to go really fast. I want to talk about mental health stuff here because it's clearly that Neb is out of his mind.
And if we're not careful, we mess this up all the time in the church, too. We instantly believe everything is a spiritual issue.
And I want to say this down to the bottom of my socks is this: there are some mental health things that are clearly related to spiritual issues.
There are also things that are clearly related to physical issues, and in that moment, you need a doctor and you need medicine.
There are also issues connected to trauma, and in that instance, you need a counselor.
I would also tell you there are moments and instances where it is related to spiritual issues, and changing your perspective and putting your eyes solely on Jesus, he is a deliverer.
In that moment, you need a deliverer, and he can and will deliver you. It's why you hear stories of people saying, "I was addicted. I was stuck in this. I met Jesus," and instantly everything changed.
They were delivered. There's no shame in medicine if you need medicine. There's no shame in counseling if you need counseling, and there is no shame in turning to Jesus if you need deliverance.
That's what Nebuchadnezzar did, and what happens is, and if you want more information on that, there's a great book called "Grace for the Afflicted" by Matthew Stanford out of Houston. A phenomenal book. Read that.
But here's what I want you to know. Daniel stays faithful to Jesus, and God uses him in a big way. My conclusion is this: Church, we need the Holy Spirit.
Daniel was able to act supernaturally because of the Holy Spirit. Second, pride will destroy you. It will make you go crazy.
Because you will think it all revolves around you, and none of us can handle that weight and that pressure, and it will drive us nuts.
And lastly, Jesus can and will deliver you if you trust him and make him your king. Father, we love you.
We thank you that you love us, and we thank you that we have the opportunity to be delivered in moments and areas where we need deliverance. In Jesus' name, amen.